well let's let's get going so welcome
everyone uh nice to see so many people
what's online
um so this is a an afternoon devoted to
uh applied category Theory
a lot of you in the audience would have
heard me speak about category Theory
before
um
what is applied category three is going
to be the question
Okay so
and I'm particularly interested in
getting philosophers on board trying to
you know I fell in love with category
Theory 30 years ago
um you know when you fall in love with
something you kind of want everybody
everyone else should see the beauty of
the thing you fall in love with uh it's
been a bit of an uphill battle perhaps
to get philosophers interested
so when Yale University announced uh
they're officially replacing the grad
program logic requirement with a broader
formal methods requirement that they can
go off and study logic probability stats
Game Theory
I tweeted back teach them category
theories why not you can have all of
those at the same time if you just give
them a basic a basic grounding
accountability Theory we can do all of
all of the above with just a few little
add-ons
foreign
so yeah I mean philosophers typically
through their training
you know almost inevitably will
encounter propositional logic uh and
some first order logic depends where you
are perhaps a modal logic too because
they'll they'll be dealing with uh
metaphysics and they want to know about
the issues to do with this St
possibility and so on
if yeah plus some people will be exposed
to second order logic perhaps some
probability Theory decision Theory and
so on
unlikely or perhaps I mean this isn't a
scientific survey I just say people will
pop up and say oh yeah my department we
do this this it may be but I mean I
think in general it's probably fair to
say that something like type Theory
would be unlikely to be studied uh in a
philosophical training and category
Theory really very very unlikely
okay now of course you can be exposed to
these things in different ways and I'm
kind of more interested
in in
bringing about quite a shift in Attitude
should we say because if you approach if
you
if you approach things in a certain kind
of way if you project yourself from the
top down you know you could be exposed
to category three
um just by a well
um yeah that's the first order logic and
now I can express cash query Theory as
some sort of first order Theory uh you
know oh it's to do with a collection of
things a collection of of objects and a
collection of
connections arrows between these objects
and it satisfies this and this and this
property
so you could see it as just a sort of
specific Theory
uh within within a kind of existing
formalism
but if you do that you don't really kind
of get at the heart the the heuristic
heart of the matter you don't get the
mindset that comes from the sort of
correct instruction into category Theory
and that's more of what I'm interested
in
so we're talking about I mean there's a
slightly controversial though like this
language we'll see what has come to mean
this apply category Theory later but you
know there have been applications of
Category 3 right from the beginning very
beginning so it gets going in the 40s uh
within mathematics itself there's a you
know there's this great effort to
systematize sorts of situations when you
you've got a kind of kind of entity
maybe maybe like a category of spaces or
collection of spaces and you want to
know things about the spaces uh and
they're very hard to deal with in
themselves but if only you could
transfer them somewhere more amenable to
you maybe into some sort of sub
collection of algebraic objects you can
resolve questions back in the in the
geometric side yeah the spatial Side by
this transfer over to something uh
algebraic
okay so you're finding these sort of
patterns these common patterns appearing
between these different areas of
mathematics
from the 40s onwards this this becomes
you know uh popular approach through the
60s I mean these are yeah these are
approximate dates you'll find uh
exceptions all over but you start to get
people thinking you know in this
category is pretty pretty good maybe I
didn't need to see it uh in terms of oh
it's it's it's just a kind of a
categories are sort of set with some
properties maybe I can make it its own
foundations and there's a
recently departed William levier in the
60s who who suggests exactly that the
category Theory could provide its own
foundations
and later on in the 60s he's even so
absolutely fundamental Construction in
Casper
the notion of adjoint Android Junctions
or joint functions so this is very much
when you've got the situation and you've
got to sort of transfer in one direction
from from one space to another space
and it might not be the case that you
can just reverse that process and hedge
yourself back second place back to the
first place but that you could do
something as as good as you can it's the
sort of best approximation to kind of
reversing the process
these things are adjunctions and Lavere
discovers whether they were there even
in your first order logic they were
there right right and you're very very
fundamental you know those quantifiers
you dealt with
those Universal and existential
quantifiers themselves are part of that
process of this this reversal
okay so category through sort of seeping
right into the roots of the very basic
formalisms
okay then computer science uh gets going
over if that dates fair enough I mean
maybe it's even earlier uh we've got
computer scientists here uh who can tell
us perhaps about that uh and we'll kind
of get a sense perhaps a little sense of
why why they got interested in their
physics perhaps from the 80s
so we're gonna have John Baez when he
wakes up he's in California so I guess
you know we had to push his talk back to
to five to give him time to wake up so
what is it in California it's pretty
early so I think he's not with us at the
moment
um so he wrote a paper with a student of
his Mike stay in 2009
um it's called it's a Rosetta Stone
physics topology logic and computation
just to see that can you perhaps the
people are here a bit
smaller I mean
um so category theory has been used to
understand uh ideas in physics topology
logic and computation
so it's always about you have a kind of
entity of a kind and then you've got
mappings between these adjectives that
stuff the thing that interests you so
physics you're interested in in Hilbert
espec if you're doing quantum mechanics
you're interested in Filbert spaces and
you're interested in operators between
Hilton spaces
okay if you're interested in topology
you might be uh interested in a space
that has a boundary an input boundary
and an output boundary and you're
interested in the manifold that joins
the input to the output
if you're dealing with logic you're
interested in having a proposition and
an inference through to another
proposition
with computation you have data types
data inputs uh various kinds people put
in their data and then it gets processed
and after you comes through the other
end into the output
okay and these parallels go on I mean so
that they'll be uh you know famously
with uh when you put when you put two
Quantum systems together they don't just
they're not just a straightforward
product of their parts you can't just
separate them off again
entanglement ideas
um but still all of a sudden you you put
two Quantum systems together and you
want to the the space of these two
Quantum systems is this tensor product
and in topology you're going to form the
disjoint unit you're going to put your
kind of input spaces together
uh next to each other and so on in logic
it's exactly the same as forming
conjunctions
X and Y uh and in computation the
product of data types and so on and so
forth so you're getting these these very
similar ideas of just being manifested
right across the board
okay so that we've got this uh
fun
expression at a certain point um they've
got a bit controversial somebody wanted
to call it computational trinitarianism
and some people didn't like the kind of
spooky theological tone to it so it
sometimes gets re designated as
computational trilogy
uh okay but this idea that these things
are just part and parcel so it's not
just that there's an analogy going on
it's that they really are three faces of
the same thing
called the father son who only goes to
kind of idea okay so computation spaces
and logic they're just they're just
three size of the same thing with the
thought that therefore if you make an
advance in any one of these areas they
don't to manifest itself in one of the
other other areas
foreign
it's really that tight if you see it
from this point of view
okay now that we're going to still have
to head off and start a different
direction
very good things are still going on
devoted quite a lot of my life to this
sort of thing
so book 2020 model Copy Type Theory
suggesting that um
a very good thing if if philosophers got
on board with this language
um
yeah all sorts of ways I think
philosophers could use this this these
kind of ideas I mean if people know
there's people work on category mistakes
uh Gilbert Wiles ideas have been updated
I mean
everything the computer science
scientist wants to do by controlling
input data to be of the right type and
this is so close to the kind of idea of
category steps that Ryan was worrying
about back in the 30s and 40s
uh
yeah I'm gonna
give you another talk in a couple of
weeks on on I mean it really lends
itself the the kind of Brandon Robert
Brandon's approach to to inferentialism
I think it could be beautifully realized
in this program but that's not for today
um yeah another recent bit of work I did
which was which was really trying to
sort of Chase up the the
passage the path that takes us right up
to you know the kind of cutting edge of
category Theory uh and type Theory means
physics
it's something expressed in this paper
here which is is kind of pointing to
this work just to point out so this this
kind of work goes on that's really
really kind of cutting-edge model type
Theory meets physics
right up in that highest highest Heights
of theories of quantum gravity and
whether you think that's going to work
or not but it's coming much much closer
down to earth now
some of the work they're doing out there
which is is looking at Quantum computate
computations down to earth
but it's a closer to Earth in quantum
gravity anyway uh using using this this
linear homotopy type Theory the linear
of linear logic but again this is not
today's work
because we're going somewhere slightly
different so
yeah the further set of applications
starts to take place let's date it from
the 2010s although maybe you can again
you can plug precursors and what's that
looking at
okay well these are people scattered
through the country uh I'm sorry through
the world but pretty well represented in
the UK
[Music]
but they're looking at things like
causality probabilistic reasoning
statistics learning theory deep neural
networks dynamical systems information
Theory database Theory natural language
processing cognition Consciousness
systems biology genomics epidemiology
chemical reaction networks Neuroscience
complex networks Game Theory robotics
Quantum Computing and the list goes on
okay so we're away now from the very
sort of high-end physics applications
and we're dealing with some you know
some some sort of things that of course
philosophers should be very interested
in
okay and and in a sense it shouldn't be
such a surprise because
I mean you're dealing with but if you
notice back there that list they're
dealing both with physical processes the
various natural processes out there in
the world and then they're also dealing
with inferential processes
okay so kind of interestingly uh the
category theory is good at dealing with
both because they're both to do with
movement of certain kinds of starting
place to a finishing place
if you want to go all hegelian on us
you're kind of unifying that subjective
and objective logic
people tend not to use hegel's language
these days
and yeah I mean something all over the
place uh
these these these string diagrams
if you
oops
just click anywhere any any sort of
Applied category Theory you just get
this end of this beautiful diagrams
these 2D grams lots of wiring diagrams
going on reverse clients wiring things
with nodes
um right across the board and in fact
this is this is kind of one of the ways
that uh well there's any I think John
buyers will tell us about it at five
o'clock
but he he was just fascinated by the way
you found these these very similar
diagrams across engineering and
chemistry and biology and so on and so
forth and there had to be something in
common that unified it and he thought
everything would be
the common Essence to why these diagrams
are all appearing
um across these different domains
okay so you're going to find these all
over the shop
okay A bit of people are very interested
in this compositionality that that links
you off there's a journal now called
compositionality which is a general
devotee to this applied category Theory
and why it's so appropriate is well
there's various things you want to do
some very basic moves is is
um I mean we actually already saw it in
that Rosetta Stone thing the idea that
if you if you have one system at some
process
uh of some kind going on that takes you
from a beginning to an end we can put
together two systems in parallel
okay we can compose systems in parallel
and we have to you know again
diagrammatically it's all very obvious
why you should do that you're just
you're just sort of joining two two
diagrams and you put it them next to
each other
and you don't need very much
compatibility between the systems to do
this if on the other hand you want to
put them in series if you want to make
one process feed into the second process
you're gonna have to make sure that the
output of the first one matches the
input of the second one okay or they're
not going to join together again very
very category theoretic it wants it
wants its inputs to match its outputs
yeah or there could be something more
subtle going on there could be sort of
several inputs and several outputs and
maybe only some of the outputs being
matched by the new input to some other
new device and you could just plug in
those wires that match into the new
system
yeah or sometimes you can take a wire
coming out bend it round that could be a
useful move you might want to make as
well
uh sometimes also you've got a system
with a networking system and you've got
a little chunk of it and and you want to
replace you want to take a little box
inside uh that's that system and plug in
something more complicated with the
right inputs and outputs
so you can kind of compose by plugging
one system inside another
okay so um
this is I'm sure we're going to be
hearing a lot a lot about this over the
next two hours and a bit so Toby Toby
Smythe's uh talking first I'll give John
Bice bit more of an introduction when
it's that time for him
um so I was intrigued to you know a
Toby's work
um looking around some of the papers
he's made available and this this is his
default thesis so it's called just last
year I guess is there 22. mathematical
foundations for a compositional account
of the Bayesian brain
and we'll be hearing about that today so
primary motivation and writing this
thesis is to lay the groundwork for
well-typed notice cognitive science and
computational Neuroscience so this is
this is pretty high pretty intricate
interesting stuff this isn't just
you know simple physical processes just
going around in their simple way
um
it's it's tapping into a field that I've
been looking into a bit of late this um
this world of uh predictive processing
active inference you know the free
energy if we had sort of Carl Frist in
his big name in the field
um this yeah some interesting stuff
going on there kind of hierarchical
Bayesian models involved in the way that
we deal with the world we make all these
predictions about the way that we you
know most of the world is is sort of
fantasized by us it's just a slightly
constrained by our influence in some
sense
so there's all sorts of ways this very
strong top-down component to our
perceptions
uh interesting stuff
so curiously I find myself um
it would almost plug the Gap so I've you
know I've spent a lot of my life as I
say if they're interested the category
theories type Theory could spell being
interested in machine learning
bayesianism I had a formal life that
kind of pops up from time time
occasionally uh which was an early
interest in psychoanalysis and then I
wrote a co-wrote a book called
psychosomatic medicine so sort of
extraordinarily you could it could even
be this kind of bridge that takes place
between those
um so there are plenty of people that
are there's a lot of psychotherapists
now talking to this active inference
approach to the mind you know the brains
are kind of optimizers the trouble is
that very often they get kind of caught
in sub-optimal optimizations you can get
locked in in a certain kind of way and
the heavy top-down processing sort of
makes it very difficult to sort of shift
shift the system and gets kind of locked
in a certain certain way I mean you know
for example delusions for example uh
cases where there's such a sort of
strong top downness to the to the sexual
apparators that the input from the world
does nothing to constrain or not enough
to constrain from the delusions so it's
a very extreme case but all sorts of
psychiatrics
light
um yeah so gosh if if Toby can help us
sort of plug the Gap here I think we can
be kind of fun if I could if I could
bridge the gap of my interests so I'm
certainly very much looking forward to
hear what he's going to say today
um
I noticed this rather longer bit it's
taken from his thesis
this well-timed cognitive science and
computational neurosense
and and it's got yeah so types types of
what render these these Concepts
precisely allow categorical models to be
cleanly compositional so it's again
there's very much things I've been
talking about this sort of plugging
together if the interface is right
so I think this is something that maybe
a
from what I've seen of the active
inference literature well I've been
intrigued to see if if he can make that
something more category theoretic meet
the active inference I think this is a
really exciting project
okay
um
that's uh yeah I think that that brings
us the end of the introduction because
uh we're keeping rigidly on time and
here we go it's 10 10 to 10 to four so
let me
close down my thing
uh stop sharing
that's again can you share Now Toby
how's that uh yeah that's that's good
do we get that full screen here what do
we um
this is so useful
uh we can get it mostly full screen I
think
I'm just getting the
um
we can do that and we can do that and
there's one more thing I can do
uh
what's the other thing
well there's probably enough is it
that's probably enough I don't think I
can do it in the browser one okay yeah
that's brilliant great okay so my great
pleasure to to introduce Toby Smythe to
talk to us on Bayesian brains cyber
categorically
great thanks David and thanks to the
very warm introduction
um I'll try to live up to it
um so my my yeah so my first degree was
actually in philosophy and psychology
and
I guess it's possibly thinking also my
enjoyment or predisposition to Vicky
about things like the mind in this kind
of abstract way that possibly
philosophers are kind of um
you know you know inclined to is What's
led me to enjoy using this language that
David
um so clearly loves using as well
um I'm not going to be saying very much
on the sort of philosophical side today
though you know I yeah I believe as
David does that this language has a lot
to to give to philosophy what I'm going
to be doing really is
um to talk a little bit about this
journey that David nicely summarized the
beginning that I've been on um basically
trying to replace one kind of confusion
about what's really going on with this
idea that's called predictive coding in
the computational Neuroscience
literature and the sort of related set
of ideas called active inference
um with a different kind of confusion
which is all about you know category
Theory and this sort of higher
dimensional algebra that goes along with
it
um I I suspect I'm sort of I'm in a
happier place with that second kind of
confusion it suits me better but I also
think that
it it helps us to understand a kind of
idea which at least as far as I was
concerned wasn't very well wasn't wasn't
crisply or clearly expressed so far in
the literature that had been written in
computational Neuroscience possibly
because yeah they're the interest is in
specific models or specific bits of the
brain whereas my interest is really in
just you know what brains do or more
generally what adaptive systems do
um and what's emerging now in the apply
category Theory World bringing together
all those different
um
domains that were listed on that slide
earlier
um is this kind of
this idea this this thing called
categorical cybernetics
um it sort of uses this kind of nice
General language of category Theory to
bring together ideas in in you know
economic theory and machine learning and
reinforcement learning and computational
Neuroscience and show what are the
commonalities and allow people as a
result to talk to each other a bit
better and to understand what they're
really thinking about in terms in each
other's language a bit better
and so what I'm going to do is maybe
sketch some of this I'm going to try not
to assume too much you know background
in either Neuroscience or in mathematics
or particularly in category Theory
um I'm going to talk about this idea of
the Bayesian brain and this related idea
of predictive coding I'm going to talk
about
um kind of current understanding of
probability Theory using this
compositional language I'm going to talk
about Dynamics and I'm going to talk
about how we could see predictive coding
is basically a way of translating
certain kinds of statistical models
expressed in this first compositional
language to
kind of uh compositional dynamical
systems that are expressed in the second
language and so when David was talking
about how categories are really useful
for talking about things like
translation between you know different
mathematical languages that's really
what we're making use of here
okay the first thing I want to do though
is to say a little bit more about what I
mean or what people mean when they talk
about the base of your brain
um and this later set of ideas called
the free energy principle and predictive
coding
um it's a very sort of prominent idea in
computational Neuroscience
um and you know it may be a slightly
controversial too but it's it's a claim
that most of what the brain does
um and indeed sort of most of what's
kind of living systems or adaptive
systems do generally can be understood
as approximate Bayesian inference
and so what that means is that you have
a system and it's it's trying to predict
what's going on in the world more
precisely maybe protect predict you know
what it's it's what What sentences
receiving
and then on the basis of the sense data
it does receive update its beliefs about
the structure of the world or what's out
there in order to make its predictions
um better or more veridical
um and this thing called the free energy
is a quantity that you can optimize
um in order to do inference of this kind
you know kind of better way or to
improve your doing of inference and if
you if you minimize this quantity at
least in certain contexts you get
dynamical systems
um which look a bit like dynamical
systems that people had already written
down earlier in the literature in
computational Neuroscience that relate
to various bits of say the visual cortex
and and so that alignment says you know
it says to a lot of people okay well
maybe this is what those circuits are
actually doing
um one of the difficulties you get in if
you're just going straight from you know
the statistical model that you might be
interested in to dynamical systems
you're going very manually
um is that
there are kind of a lot of moving parts
and particularly if you go from one
situation to another you might have to
Red arrive all of your Dynamic equations
again
um even if when you look at the brain it
has some kind of nice modular structure
and if you look at these statistical
models so they do too and this is a kind
of hint of compositionality and so it
seems to be kind of a kind of neater
thing to do to see what the essence is
of this process and to try to you know
make this translation once in a
compositional way so that you don't need
to do it over and over again and you
know end up with very sort of
impenetrable papers full of difficult
equations
you just end up with in financial papers
that require you to know a language that
you maybe didn't already know but I
think what I hope is that people start
to learn mathematics in a in a
compositional way in the future and so
that these these papers or this work
that is expressed in this category
theoretic language
um doesn't you know scare people off in
the way I'm gonna sit here this might do
now I can hear some yeah
online
is that you John
could you please yes
that's right thanks
um okay so I mean I don't want to spend
too long talking about why category
Theory because David's done a very good
job already
um I'm just gonna say some sort of you
know some general say some generalities
and hopefully they sound nice and
convince you that this is not a crazy
thing to be doing
that category theory is like the
mathematics of composition of sort of
pattern because it's about translation
it's about interconnection it's kind of
about metaphor too it's about saying
okay well here's this pattern it crops
up in lots of different places and maybe
this is like this other thing and that's
kind of like a kind of translation
and as we've been indicating that it
seems to promise to supply a kind of
lingua Franca for mathematical science
generally so that you know each
different sort of category of systems
could be like a little library in this
in the sense of computers and computer
programming that you can import it and
have access to all the kind of nice
tools that are available but because
it's in this common language they all
these different parts plug together very
nicely
um
and that's you know this happens because
categories they collect into this bigger
category of categories so they it's that
kind of supplies its own foundations as
David was indicating
and this allows us to use the morphisms
between the categories and themselves
these are known as functors to translate
from one of these libraries or
mathematical universes to another
um thereby sort of connecting them
together
um but so that's kind of like one major
benefit of using this language and
another one is that it kind of because
you have to say like what are the
interfaces of your system like where do
they start and where do they end or you
know what do they connect from and to
it kind of enforces this discipline it
kind of enforces a kind of clear
thinking it enforces
um an effort to carve nature at its
joints in this kind of platonic way
okay so to make a little bit more
progress at least with the mathematics I
want to try to say briefly what a
category actually is
um it's a collection I often donated
with C for category like this kind of
with this little tick in it it's a
collection of objects so these are the
things that are being related often
denoted c0 and then for each pair of
objects you have a set of ways of
relating them to each other it's a kind
of it's a set of edges or morphisms
um so if you write them like this it
goes from A to B and the key detail is
that if you have away from going away
from where to go from a A to B and then
B to C as I've drawn down here you get a
composite morphism like this and so it's
a bit more than I mean it's quite a lot
more than just a graph it's it's a graph
where the edge is compose
and this is where the compositionality
comes from
um there's also an important extra
detail which is that each object is
witnessed by amorphism of its own called
its identity and then you've got some
axioms that say okay well this
composition is associative and it's
unital with respect to that identity
um those kind of details aren't super
important for what I'm saying today but
I think I just want you to have in your
mind this notion of compositionality and
particularly uh compositionality of
morphisms
um
once you've got this structure you can
start to study it in itself as David was
also talking about and one of the things
you can do one of is prove this
fundamental theorem and it has a sort of
quite in some sense trivial but very
deep and sometimes confusing proof
um it's called the United Lemma and it
and it says something that's very
familiar to us in everyday life um and
this is a kind of um a maxim from a
linguist I think called frith
um who said You shall know uh a word by
the company it keeps and the United
Lemma generalizes this to all the these
categorical contexts that you shall know
an object by the company it keeps in the
sense that if you know how a thing is
related to the other things in its new
year then
you can identify the thing itself and
that you know we know not just from
Linguistics but if you know how to get
to a place from the places around it
then you can you know figure out what
where that place is on the map so you
can sort of identify that place
um and it's a very it's a kind of very
it's a very powerful result and it's a
kind of nice
kind of nice evidence that category
Theory captures something about the way
the world is built up
okay
but the thing that you know I want to
talk about really today is the brain and
uh using the tools of categorical
cybernetics to model it
um so the brain is this nice complex
system it's made up of other complex
systems so it's made up of neurons which
of course have a lot of structure of
their own and it has this kind of
computational behavior it does
prediction and it does planning and it
does all these things that we have
programmed computers to do now
um and you know brains themselves
compose into bigger systems societies so
it has a lot of features that make it
you know that seem to suggest it should
be amenable to description to
description in this categorical language
um and indeed it should be comparable to
other other systems that people have
started to study in category Theory or
in applied category Theory cybernetic
systems
um this really I guess
at least in this form kicked off with
the the um
introduction of compositional Game
Theory by Jules Hedges and his
colleagues
um and so there they study economic
systems
um and those are very closely related to
systems of reinforcement learning
um and indeed structurally also related
to systems in machine learning as it is
in the form that you know is given rise
to things like chap GPT
and these things all have a similar kind
of structure there's some kind of
process which might have some kind of
control input
and then you know there's another part
which goes backwards a kind of
retroductory part a sort of feedback
process
and the process and possibly the control
and the feedback you could think of them
as all being contained within one system
that is in kind of traditional
cybernetic maybe called a plant or in
control control theory called a plant
but this is really just like a part of a
bigger system it's open to some
environment and the brain has you know
similar structure at least in these kind
of visual cortical areas that have these
predictive coding model models that I
um introduced at the beginning and so
there like a little bit of neural
circuitry maybe has one part which
points from deep inside the brain here
to out towards the world here
and it does say prediction about what
what you know the eye should expect to
receive and then there's another set of
neurons which goes from nearer the world
to deeper inside the brain that that
feeds back the error in that prediction
and allows the brain to form a sort of
updated or new belief in Bayesian um
probability it's called the posterior
belief and so you have this kind of
bi-directional process which looks a bit
like a kind of cybernetic Loop
and so I'm interested in not just the
brain of course the brain is a great
Target and obviously I I um you know
part of me as a brain I want to
understand that
um but I'm interested in systems that do
this kind of thing adaptive systems in a
sort of General way and because of that
um I'm I'm Keen to use these General
tools uh and to study this system that
is so good at doing this kind of
adaptation which is the brain
okay and so you've seen me draw on the
previous slide a diagram and it's a
diagram of the kind that if you know
about category Theory or you did some
searching as David was suggesting is
known as a string diagram and so I want
to introduce categories again or at
least composition again using this
language
so that when I use these diagrams again
a bit later you'll know what I know what
I'm doing
the great thing about using string
diagrams is of course for most of us we
have this very well developed visual
system
and so we can not only use category
Theory to reason about it but we can
also use it to help us reason about
mathematical things like categories
themselves in particular you know when
we use pen and paper it's a
two-dimensional medium and it's a kind
of often for processes where things can
go in parallel as well as sequentious
sequentially it's often more convenient
to draw the processes out as we see when
people draw other kinds of more informal
diagrams than it is to write them in
this kind of more sort of traditional
algebraic symbolic way that you could
write on on that I've drawn on the right
hand side
and so what we can do is if we have a
process F that goes from A to B so we're
going to start by reading on the left
and then if you have another process G
that goes from B to C we can plug them
in and so then you have a process that's
G after F which in traditional
mathematical notation is denoted like
this
and so that's like the sequential
composition and we can also put another
process H from X to Y by the side of it
and so this thing now goes from the
tensor a tensor X to C tensor why
um and you have as I said each object
has an identity morphism and this is
just what the string itself represents
and you can put this next to you know
processes and you know you can use this
to plug things together
um you have special processes that start
in like the empty diagram which we write
with this I and they we think of as like
States so in in physics they would be
like vectors or in probability Theory
they're like distributions
um and then you have things that go the
other way that sort of terminated an
empty diagram and these might represent
like
um
say uh predicates on some space or they
might represent effects that you could
measure or measurements on your physical
system
and these are kind of morphisms in the
other direction in into this other into
this unit diagram into this unit object
and with these diagrams UK you can not
only sort of depict the processes
themselves but you can write down
equations and start to manipulate the
diagrams accordingly and so here at the
bottom as an example I've written the
equation that represents the
co-associativity of
um of copying so it says if you copy
once and then you copy one of the copies
it doesn't matter which one of the
copies you you've copied and you know
this has this nice kind of Fairly
obvious graphical representation here
which is a bit more I think natural to
use at least for this kind of thing
um than the sort of algebraic sort of
symbolic notation that maybe is more
familiar to people from mathematics
one of the things
um that we can represent in this
language is probability Theory
um and this you know the kind of natural
kind of length you know mathematical
formalism to to use for that is that of
Markov kernels which you could really
think of as like conditional probability
distributions and so here I've got this
thing C it goes from X to Y and we could
think of this as like a pro conditional
probability distribution
of Y given X
but now we have them these things in
this compositional language we can plug
them together so if we have one and then
another we can
compose them together by sort of
marginalizing over the middle thing and
this says okay well we'll sample an
output
we'll sample an output from Y and then
we'll give it to Z give it to D and then
we'll run whatever presses D represents
and that'll give us something in a
distribution in Z and so this is like
some something it's like d after c
Z given X
we can do copying in probability two and
this is like you know it descends a
thing to the Delta Distribution on the
copy x equals x Prime which you might be
familiar with
and so here we can and we can use this
to formalize in this kind of graphical
language joint distributions
and so here we've got a joint
distribution with one thing on with one
module on X and a kind of what's called
a probability a likelihood which goes
from X to y
and this thing depicts the kind of
this sort of um this representation of
the joint distribution is like a
likelihood a conditional probability
distribution on Y and a prior and this
is the kind of one fundamental part of
Bayes law that you might be familiar
with
and as I indicated on the previous slide
these kind of co-states or effects they
represent things which we could think of
in probability as like fuzzy predicates
um and that might be something that if
you're philosophically inclined you've
thought about
we're not going to use them very much
but we will use them to represent loss
functions in machine learning and in
predictive coding later on
okay
so at the heart of this kind of uh
predictive coding idea is Bayesian
inference and what Bayesian inference
does is effectively takes one process
here this goes we're reading the diagram
upwards now just you know first reasons
of space
here this goes from X to Y and so we can
think of this as predicting something in
y given something in X but you know it's
a kind of stochastic prediction it's
fuzzy
and so Bayesian inversion allows us to
go to go instead of from this process
which goes from X to Y to a process
which goes um from
y to X here
and so this is like reversing this
process it allows us to say okay given
what I observed what should my belief
what might be a better belief have been
and the the Criterion that it satisfies
is that the kind of these are two ways
of writing the same joint distribution
so you start with a prior belief that
says okay well this is how I think the
world is
and then you have this way of generating
data
and this says okay well
this The Joint distribution you get over
the say causal structure of the world
and the observations is the same whether
you go forwards or backwards and so this
this kind of makes it like a
well-behaved inversion so it's a kind of
it's a kind of fuzzy way of inverting
this this predictive process
and Bayes law is often written like this
thing it's just a way of expressing the
conditional probability in the other
direction and it just comes out of the
kind of laws of probability that you
might be familiar with um this is the
product rule of of distributions
but I'm not I'm not here to give a
tutorial about
um you know about
fundamental probability Theory I'm going
to try to build up to predictive coding
I've start I've already introduced
categorical probability Theory and I
want to get from there in the kind of
piecemeal way from like simple steps
using like simple you know simple like
compositional Parts towards the
dynamical systems that represent how the
brain does this inferential process
actually dynamically
um and so as I indicated you know a
brain
it has lots of parts that may sort of
plug into one another in particular it
has some parts of the brain which are
nearer the retinal the eye and other
parts of the brain which are kind of
what we think of as more sort of high
level that represent you know
objects or concepts rather than say like
what we might think of on a computer as
pixels and so some somewhere in the
brain you have to go from these kind of
low level features to the high level
high level ideas and this happens in
this kind of hierarchical way
so zooming out piece by piece and so you
know you might imagine being say at the
cinema and you're sitting right at the
front and you're looking at you know
looking at the screen but you can only
fit in your visual field say a part of
the screen at one time but yet you can
sort of keep track of what's going on
everywhere and so you maybe have this
process where you've got you know a
belief about what's happening on the
whole screen
and also another process where the eye
is receiving signals from part of it
and if the first thing that happens is
your brain updates the belief about
what's going on in that little part and
then it can update using that new belief
yeah the you know the sort of higher
level belief about what's going on on
the whole in the whole scene or in the
story more generally and this is a
hierarchical process and really it's got
this kind of compositional structure
and so we might wonder okay given in
this kind of abstract language a sort of
Kernel from X to Y and another one D
from y to Z
what its inversion is so what is the
inversion of the composite Channel or
kernel
um and how does it relate to the
inversions of the parts and so this is a
kind of question about the
compositionality of Bayesian inversion
and it's not only relevant in predictive
coding of course it's relevant in all
sorts of contexts particularly in
um you know say things like uh
probabilistic machine learning and
things like that
and so it's actually quite easy to show
that the composition of of
um the inversions
gives you the composition of but gives
you the inversion of the composite
Channel
um an important thing to notice from
these pictures is that the inversion
say if we just go back to this this this
kind of defining law this is what we
could think of as a kind of abstract
base law
that the inverse channel here
the whole law in fact but particularly
the inverse Channel depends on the
choice of Prior because if I took if I
change this if I change it to Pi prime
it wouldn't necessarily satisfy this Law
And so there's a kind of dependence here
you see it comes in in the in the in the
sort of defining equation here you've
got Pi popping up
and so we can't just sort of in some
sense reverse the channel directly we
need to say okay well what is this prior
that I'm reversing it with respect to
and so we'll see okay well if we use
this law twice we can you know invert
first of all d
but you see we've got C coming in first
and so that the the prior for this
inversion of D is C after pi
and if we invert you know if we invert
if we invert oh sorry we should invert C
first the prior is pi and then we invert
D afterwards but the prior is C after Pi
we get this composited version
over here
and so this says okay well we can
decompose
the Bayesian inversion of a composite
channel in terms of the inversions of
the factors here and here
and in particular this kind of dip this
kind of structure this dependence what
is this this thing how does this arise
if we try to package this up neatly we
will end up using what is called a lens
and this is something that's already
been used in categorical cybernetics and
in categorical dynamical systems theory
um and then all sorts of bits of
category Theory already
to formalize these kinds of binary
processes and so it's very nice and so
maybe somehow mathematically inevitable
but this kind of formalization also
happens to be the way that Bayesian
inversions compose
and so we can say a little bit about
this
so I've indicated that
these inversions
see this is the inversion of the channel
C on the previous slide c x to y
the inversions they depend on the priors
and the prior is a state on
the domain of the channel
and so we call the inversions which we
might write to see it's dagger for you
know technical reasons it's it because
it effectively makes up what's known as
in other bits of category Theory a
dagger functor but this thing is like a
state dependent Channel
and so it takes in a prior and it gives
us the channel in the backwards
Direction
so this is a function from states to
channels like this
and in fact we can compose these things
if we have a state dependent channel
from A to B and it depends on X and
another one from B to C that also
depends on X we can copy the state
that we depend on and give it to both
parts and then compose those parts
together and that you know is something
that should be hopefully quite natural
to see in this diagram if we sort of
follow along the flow of the information
through it
and this means that the state dependent
channels on a particular state so these
all depend on distributions on X but
these things form a category and we can
you know write down the morphisms the
set of morphisms in this way
so not only though do the state
dependent channels on X form a category
for each X
but also if we have a process you know
from y to X we can say re-index these
these State dependent processes
so now we can pre-compose the input to F
and F Prime and G Prime over here by say
this morphism from y to X
so now if we have a state on y
we can also feed that through p and then
feed the that composite State into F
Prime and into G Prime and still do the
same composition and so this gives us a
mapping
indeed a functor from the category stat
X
to stat y
and so that's going to be important
because as we've seen here it Maps like
this
but what we did before is we had an
inversion on D
and we pre-composed it with C to give
this thing
D dagger
C after something
and so this cap this with re-indexing
captures what's going on in the
composite inversion story
and we can sort of you know use category
Theory or categorical tools to package
all of that stuff up very nicely
we can pair an individual predictive
Channel
C with its state dependent inversion C
dagger and the pairing of a Channel or
kernel with an inversion which may or
may not be the exact Bayesian inversion
that satisfies that equation
but a pairing of that kind
is what I call a Bayesian lens
and I don't have time to explain how we
obtain the category of these things but
it is obtained using a sort of canonical
tool of category Theory called the
growth and deconstruction
so we have this index category stat of
State dependent channels a family of
categories for each possible Space X
that's compatible with this re-indexing
if you have an index category of that
kind you can apply the Groton
deconstruction and that gives you
another category that is the the
morphisms which are pairs like this
and there's a kind of composition rule
that comes out of the grid and
deconstruction which tells you how to
compose these lenses and it in fact
captures exactly what's going on with
Bayesian inversion and so Bayesian
inversion at least it's compositionality
has this nice in some sense Universal
Property but because it because it
arises in this kind of abstract way it's
not an ad hoc thing that depends on the
the situation at hand or the kind of
problem you're studying it's it's a kind
of mathematical consequence of the
structure of of you know what's going on
for in Bayesian inference
and you know we can use string diagrams
to really spell out this compositional
structure and it captures the picture I
drew earlier of this predictive and
updating process so now we have these
two two little lenses
here and here
and so one now you know goes from X to Y
and we can think of this as doing like a
high level prediction
and then here we've got another goes
from what y to Z and we can think of
this as being this lower level
prediction and we can compose those
things together to get a prediction that
goes from the high level to the lowest
level
and we can also follow the information
flow backwards so now suppose we've got
some feedback from the world here
well okay we flow through the forwards
information and this gives us the kind
of prior
um
the pro C after pi
and then this gives us an updated
intermediate level belief
and now say we had Pi here
now the inversion here takes in pi
C Prime pi and this gives us the higher
level belief and this this thing here is
exactly what we had from Bayes law
and so this is what I mean when I say
that you know the Bayesian updates
compose optically they compose according
to this lens pattern
and as I've already indicated this this
comes up a lot in categorical
cybernetics in fact this kind of chain
rule is exactly how that propagation
works and it's it's how sort of utility
is passed back in economic games
um and so it's interesting that this
this kind of nice General construction
captures all of those of all of those um
all of those situations
um and in such a way that actually
applies to this physical system that
that is the brain
so
I've said that there are some of these
lenses you know c c dagger
where this is some State dependent
channel that actually satisfies Bay's
law as I drew it a couple of slides ago
but there are lots of other lenses
where C Prime has this type the same
kind of type say it goes it takes in oh
sorry
takes in a y and it depends on some
prior in X and it gives you some new
updated X
there are lots of lots of State
dependent channels of this form and
they're not all exact Bayesian
inversions
um
we could think of them as like
approximate inversions
the way that we could formalize this
chain rule in in the kind of neatest way
of exact Bayesian inference
is as what's called a section of this
vibration so Bayesian lenses
form a category where the morphisms of
these pairs and we can sort of project
out we can forget this part just to end
up in C
and a section is effectively a mapping
from C into this vibration above it such
that if you do this round trip you get
back where you started
and what makes a mapping a functor is
that it preserves composition and so
what's going on here is that we map C to
C dagger
and we also map the to D dagger
such that if we map
DC
we get
the the inversion of DC which as we've
already seen is
this thing
see dagger after d dagger C
and so the fact that this
this mapping of channels to lenses where
the second part is the exact inversion
is a section exactly says that Bayesian
updates composed according to this law
now again this isn't the only section of
Bayesian lenses there are others
and those ones represent approximate
inversions that are particularly well
behaved because they satisfy this
compositionality property and I call
those things inference systems and and
finding an inference system is like the
first step in in sort of defining the
approximate inference process that is
predictive coding
but you know once you've got an
arbitrary inference system
you you know it might not be very good
at actually doing prediction or updating
of beliefs if we think of Bayesian
inferences like the optimal such process
and yet nonetheless you know Evolution
hasn't just picked brains to be
instantiating some like arbitrary
inference system it's chosen ones that
are actually quite good at doing
prediction and updating
and so there must be something going on
that allows Evolution effectively to
measure how good a system is and that's
what natural selection is doing
um and similarly there must be something
on
something going on that allows brains to
improve their predictions or effectively
to learn
um and
what I'm going to talk about now is how
we can equip each Bayesian lens with a
loss function effectively a way of
measuring
this this this goodness of a prediction
um but because we have this
compositionality hanging around it
satisfies some nice you know some nice
constraints that is enforced by biology
which is that neural computation is what
you know what biologists or
neuroscientists say is local
um that means that the the data required
of the computation must be available to
the neurons themselves it shouldn't
depend on something that's going on
further away in the brain the
information has to be accessible in
order for the neurons to actually do the
computation they need to do
and so because we have this
compositionality if we enforce that of
say the loss functions or of the lenses
as well that it that makes all of the
the information local to the individual
parts of the system and so that makes it
a kind of nicely biologically plausible
thing which is a bit different from what
happens in say back propagation machine
learning where changes to some parts of
the system may depend or like the way
you measure how good the performance is
sort of filters back to the whole system
at once the loss functions there aren't
necessarily compositional
um another thing that's important to
bear in mind at least um when it comes
to approximate inference systems is that
their performance kind of depends on the
problem they're trying to solve so
obviously Evolution has selected
different organisms for different niches
and so you know if you change an animal
from it one Niche and you put it in a
different environment it might not
survive as long and that's because you
know that it's you know we could say
that abstractly that's because it's
inferential performance is kind of
context sensitive it depends on the
beliefs it has about how its environment
is structured
um and it also depends on like how it
actually you know
absorbs these observations that it has
what those observations are it might be
you might not pay attention to certain
things which in one environment might be
less important than another
one example of a loss function that's
um particularly natural and relevant in
probability theory is known as the
relative entropy or the coolback library
or KL Divergence
and this measures the difference from
one well it kind of measures a distance
or Divergence
from one distribution to another on the
same space
and we'll see in a minute that these
things that these relative entropies
also themselves satisfy a nice
compositionality property which again
comes out of a gridity construction and
so it its structure is also kind of
captured by this abstract categorical
machinery
so
one of the reasons the relative entropy
is so important in a proximate inference
if you may know or have already guessed
is that if we minimize the Divergence
say between this approximate posterior
which I've written as C Prime pi
and the exact Bayesian posterior C
dagger pi
effectively what that does is it pushes
the approximation closer to the kind of
true or the optimal
um the optimal inference
and so
often people start an approximate
inference process by trying to figure
out a way to minimize this quantity
but you can see here again that we have
this dependence
of the this quantity this Divergence on
the prior because of course the
inversions depend on the prior
and on the observation so why is the
thing that goes into
yeah the system
like this we have this diagram before
and so the actual Divergence in any
particular context depends on what the
observation was
and so if what we want to do is compose
these
um these loss functions for one say one
little neural circuit and another little
neural circuit
we should figure out a way to pass the
the information of this you know this
this observation and this prior into
those loss functions
if we write down the type as I said at
the beginning this kind of discipline
about types is one of the things that
makes category Theory to me so useful if
we write down the type of this function
we'll see that it corresponds to
um one of these
effects or co-states that I drew earlier
as long as you think of it as also
depending
on this prior
so what I think I call that a state
dependent effect effectively it's a
state dependent channel that lands in
this kind of trivial kind of empty
diagram object here
what that means if we interpret this
type in the mark of Kernel language that
I introduced earlier is that it's a
function that takes in a prior and then
an observation and it gives us back a
number and in particular it could give
us back this relative entropy
and one thing that is known about the
relative entropy and in fact is quite
easy to check is that it also satisfies
a chain rule the chain rule has this
form but I you know don't need to go
into details about what it means what
what it yeah
except to say that effectively the
composition of the relative entropy for
one lens if we think of this part
and then this part
has two lenses
this we might have
a relative entropy which lands in the
positive reels for here
and a relative entropy up here and
another one up here
this chain rule says that the composite
if you apply this kind of lens
composition rule to it
the composite relative entropy or the
relative entropy of this composite lens
is equal to the kind of lens sum of the
relative entropies of the kind of
independent lenses
and so that's that's this locality that
I was referring to
so this is a nice equality
um
again this is only a particular example
of a loss function and because
if you notice here sorry I'll go back
and slide just momentarily you notice
here that the relative entropy depends
on this exact inversion
well that means in order to be able to
compute it you need to know what that
exact inversion is and actually often
the reason we want to do approximate
inference is because Computing the exact
inversions is quite hard
and so
you know we don't want to try to compute
that thing and so we need to do
something else and so these other loss
functions are available
um and the relative entry is one example
but we could we could sort of pair a
lens with another example of a loss
function
and I've given a composition rule for
lenses and I've sketched a composition
rule for the loss functions
and so these things form these kind of
pairings of lenses with loss functions
also form a category and I call this
category the category of statistical
games
and the reason I think of it as the kind
of game
um is twofold the first is that it you
know shares a lot of structure with
categories of economic games as I've
indicated already
but it also I you know it also captures
something that's quite nice you know to
think about the use about these
processes which is that you know the way
we improve our inference is by playing
this game of how can I do my inference
better so that's this statistical game
that you play
that they say these neural circuits play
so
what we've done here is we've attached
loss functions to lenses and so just as
we had a vibration by attaching
the
the inversions to the channels
themselves we've done this attaching
thing again so we've got another
vibration
and so we could ask okay so what are the
sections of this vibration so what are
the ways of assigning in a kind of nice
compositional way to each lens
a loss function
um there are various examples so one of
them as I've said is the relative
entropy that's particularly nice because
it makes this thing an equality
but there are lots of other examples
that people use in applications because
Computing the relative entropy is
difficult so we've got things which is
like the free energy which is a abound
on the relative entropy and we've got
things which is we've got something
which is slightly different we've got
the maximum likelihood which is a way of
saying okay well how do I improve my
predictions if I don't care so much
about the actual the inferences that
come out of those
the free energy I should know is
basically the sum if that is defined as
the sum
of the the relative entropy and maximum
likelihood and it's nice that if you
make that sum not only do you get
something something that's a bit easier
to compute but you also find a loss
function which kind of encourages you
both to improve your predictions that's
the maximum likelihood thing as well as
improve your inferences
in machine learning a process which does
both the Improvement of predictions and
of inferences is called an auto encoder
if you've heard that word
foreign
in Neuroscience often it's necessary to
make further approximations to get to
something that seems to be like or
possible for the brain to compute
um and so one such approximation is
known as the LaPlace approximation and
if you apply that to the free energy you
get another loss model that is as I say
lacks in the sense that
there's some other term here to make
this equation hold
so these things all form loss models
possibly lacks lost models
and that means that they are nice kind
of local compositional ways of attaching
um loss functions to these Bayesian
lenses
and indeed
um this laplacian free energy loss model
is
the kind of family of loss functions
which underlies uh say the most
prominent models of predictive coding
so we've started with these Markov
kernels or channels as I call them we've
attached um inversions to them first to
give Bayesian lenses and then we've
attached loss functions to those lenses
to give statistical games
but there's not much freedom in that
process to actually improve the loss
functions because once you've fixed a
lens that's it the only thing you can
change is the input either the kind of
belief the prior belief you start with
or the input you get from the world what
if to improve the loss function you also
need to change the lens itself
so we can use the same kind of idea that
gave us State dependent channels here
and parameterize the the Bayesian lenses
and the loss functions to give um
parameterized lenses and statistical
games and in machine learning in
particular it's updating these
parameters is is what happens during the
training of models and in models of
neural circuits
um it's we can think of the sort of
synaptic weights on the neurons as the
parameters
and parameterizing a structure is
something that is kind of um
quite well well known in category Theory
and particularly in categorical
cybernetics
um and the way I like to think of it is
as the kind of choice of process so you
get something which takes in a Theta and
gives you a morphism
and you can compose those morphisms
themselves
and then learning amounts to kind of
improving that choice process
so
you know this is just a particular it's
a general morphism in the category C but
we can make this category the category
of statistical games
and then we have a statistical game
which depends on some parameter
and then we can optimize the loss
functions which are of course part of
the morphisms of these games
with respect to those parameters and we
can do that you know with respect to
each parameter on each component in this
kind of local way
as neural circuits seem to do and
exactly this is how predictive coding
models are obtained
so as I said we've we've paired
predictive Channels with State dependent
inversions
um these exact inversions constitute a
section
and other other sections other lenses
represent approximate inversions we can
pair the lenses with loss functions in
the same kind of way to give statistical
games
and this formalizes the chain rule of
the relative entropy
the free energy is another example of
one of these loss models and then we can
make space for learning by introducing
parameters
I'm aware I don't have much time left
and so I won't spend an awful lot of
time on Dynamics
um
I just want to say that the same kind of
idea of filling in boxes so earlier I
drew a box and I added a parameter into
it
we can use that to give
um a notion of kind of compositional
dynamical system and I think John's
going to talk more about this later
possibly I mean a lot of what John has
done is about dynamical systems
um and so
what we can do is say okay well we've
got a category that represents the
interfaces of our dynamical systems and
then we can use the morphisms of that
category to represent how those systems
are kind of wired together and this this
this category of interfaces and wirings
is something I'm going to call Int
and then on each interface so this is
the interface which has inputs X and
inputs y we have a category of dynamical
systems which take in interfaces X and Y
and so here we can fill in one system
and here we can fill another system and
you can see that this is the same again
the same pattern that we saw earlier of
an indexed category and so here the
re-indexing is the rewiring of systems
and so what we can do is apply this
wiring to the systems themselves to get
a sort of bigger system on this
composite you know on this on this out
for this outer box a kind of composite
system
then we can Define dynamical systems
which emit the data of Bayesian lenses
I call these these systems cilia because
they're like the ciliary muscle of an
eye they control the lens
um I won't go into details about the
structure I just wanted to write it down
for reference
but a cilia the Cilia have the same type
as the lenses
um but they're now sort of dynamical
lenses and so a psyllium of this type
that goes from XA to YB it has a state
space
it has a forwards output Channel that's
parameterized by the state space
uh backwards inversion that's also
parameterized by the state space and
then an update function or an update map
which is like a stochastic dynamical
system which takes in a state space and
an observation and a prior belief and
gives a new element of the state space
and so that's like the the sort of
updated parameters that we used for
learning
and these things compose by composing
the lenses together and by forming like
the the product of the of the um of the
parameter spaces so you have a parameter
on each on each bit of the composite
system
and this so this story it starts to give
us a general recipe for predictive
coding systems which we could think of
as like local approximate inference
systems you know we have parameterized
kernels we form lenses then we make
statistical games the first is the thing
I call an inference system and the
second is a lost model
and then we've gone from a parameterized
statistical game into this dynamical
category they say doing optimization as
David mentioned at the beginning on the
loss functions
and so a process that starts in this
category of stochastic maps and ends in
dynamical systems that do inversion is
something I like to call an approximate
inference Doctrine it tells you a way to
do approximate inference for each
channel in your original category
so
I will end briefly I just want to say
finally that this is all about
approximate inference effectively
perception we can extend this to active
systems
um by saying that the CIS the the agent
say is trying to predict not only
um what it perceives but also what it
should do
um effectively predict everything on its
on its interface the inputs as well as
the outputs in the literature in
neuroscience and um
related areas this interface is almost
known as its markup blanket
and so we can also package up systems
that do this kind of prediction into a
category
or if we call the interface P we get a
whole category of agent Agent P of
Agents with that interface to do this
kind of prediction
and indeed we can rewire these things
according to wiring of the kind I
mentioned earlier
so you could think of that as like if
you get in the car like the your your
sort of interface changes because you
you know you're you're now contained
within the car but the car itself has
some intelligent Behavior
you could think of a corporation which
again is made up of lots of Agents but
it itself has this legal personhood
and so at this point we start to
consider how agents themselves compose
um and this kind of gets to some
subtleties which are kind of more
philosophical questions
um in particular
um
that agents
they need to predict not only how the
environment causes their sense data but
they also need to predict not only their
senses itself but also how the
environment causes that sense data
and that's something a bit like theory
of mind and this is something that's
necessary to make this structure
compositional
um and then
once we have this you might think okay
well two different agents May disagree
about how how they're wired together and
that that we need we need a way of sort
of coming to overcoming that that sort
of disagreement
um this is really a sign that these
Bayesian models are kind of inherently
subjective and there are various ways we
can deal with that um in mathematics
there's a lot of stuff a lot of work
done in cohomology to measure
disagreements of various kinds
um and we can use diffusion to sort of
smooth out these disagreements or we
could just have a higher level agent
which imposes a resolution to the
disagreement and because of the
compositionality of all of this we can
do this or do each make each of these
choices in a kind of nicely modular way
as I say the choice depends on the
situation at hand
and so finally
this this kind of points to the kind of
broad ambition of what's known as the
free energy principle which as I said at
the beginning asserts that kind of all
adaptive systems
um at least that maintain their
interface can be understood as
performing approximate Bayesian
inference
and at least I don't believe that this
claim although it's been stated and
there's lots of evidence has been
supplied to substantiated I don't think
it's been sort of conclusively
established
and I think using categorical tools and
this formalism of compositional Acts of
inference is a nice framework in which
it might be possible to do and so what
I've talked about is a mapping that goes
from Agents
um
as say statistical models to dynamical
systems
and the free energy principle claims
that there's a mapping in the other
direction which goes from sort of
dynamical systems in say of other sort
of physical kind to
um agents or statistical models in a
world that kind of has a more sort of
biological flavor and we can sort of
think of this as a kind of mind-body
dualism and in particular one way that
we might be able to formalize this claim
is as an adjunction which is something
again I think David mentioned at the
beginning
um
thank you I know that was quite fast but
I wanted to cover a lot of ground to say
how how there's quite a lot of you know
great stuff to be you know found by
using categorical methods for complex
systems like the brain
yeah philosophy talks they sort of
always leave a very long time to for the
audience to sort of Slash it the
speakers arguments but um obviously
we're not we're not in that domain here
but perhaps if we have one one or two
questions
which
which actually I did I did there was a
thought because we've got somebody here
who works on explainable AI PhD student
and what do you do so so say you've
trained you've trained a neural net up
and you've got these sort of different
different levels if each level is to be
seen as a Bayesian lens of some kind
I mean how do I get it what is what is
the type that is the output of one layer
and the input to the next layer how can
I get to understand what it means it
sounds like you've already got the type
articulated doesn't it if you're if
you're
confusing these yes so that's I think
that gets to a point that the category
theory is kind of more about composing
systems and decomposing them so I'm
assuming yes that you started with
um two lenses
that represent say your models of small
parts of the system and you're trying to
use that to build up a bigger system but
yes if you have a kind of big
complicated neural network
um there might be various ways of
partitioning it into smaller components
to try to understand it but I'm not sure
um I have a kind of nice Universal story
about how to do that right now
um I'd love to have a good connection
from this to
um to that kind of explainable AI but I
think a sort of less ambitious aim that
we start to get from this kind of
toolkit is one that says okay well at
least we know how our systems are built
and we know what the different parts are
if we work like this if you look at
machine learning code as it is it's
often full of lots of you know very
informal commentary because people need
to
sort of be careful about where certain
bits are which how the information flows
effectively which index goes to which
other index
um and so I think people actually don't
understand the models as they are right
now
um
having some types on those interfaces
might make that process a bit easier
okay great so thanks thanks very much
always one one question from we've got
Mark here from a PhD student yeah thank
you so much for that it was a lot
very very intense and I really did
appreciate that
um there's uh the there's something that
I want to get on first of all I like the
uh an explanation of the um
impregnitiveness of the whole project uh
um but uh the the question I I want to
ask you is uh it doesn't seem like
there's going to necessarily be a clear
uh demarcation on the biological side
the ancient biology side to uh the uh
the process of uh of um of uh going from
uh um uh Bayesian lensing to the Celia I
can see institutions and uh I think you
hinted on that corporations and uh uh uh
um uh the you know the uh the focus of
uh of uh at the Cilia level might end up
being at uh uh so I want to know what
your your thoughts on that are
yes it's very interesting so I yeah I
this is a this is a kind of scale free
theory in some sense
um I don't mind I don't think of a
particular
neuron as being more like adaptive than
a whole brain or a corporation they can
all be understood as doing this process
at least on this account
um and so there's not nothing to say
that say a corporation is somehow less
like biological than sort of a single or
multi-celled small organism and in fact
I think what we see of the process of
the evolution of life itself is a kind
of growing
um sort of growth of complexity like you
start with these single celled organisms
you get multicellular organisms you get
you know you know simple plant life
animal life and now we've got societies
and in biology you have smaller
societies like ant hills and those
things are all kind of sent you know
sensitive sensible conglomerates of
their own kind and they are adaptive
systems
um and I'm trying to capture this
process in its generality
um yeah corporations are part of that
but you know nation states and the whole
world is one two
um so I I'm not trying to make a
distinction between biological systems
as they're commonly understood and these
kind of broader economic systems I think
of those things as all kind of
ecological in some sense and to be
honest I think economics could do a lot
better if it started to think a little
bit more ecologically too
okay
thank you so much
thanks very much TV
so we've got a few minutes to set up uh
what have we got three four minutes till
we get to the hour and uh
and we can hear from John hi hey John
how's it going oh yeah great
can you can we try to try out the uh it
worked with Toby so it should work with
you if I get the people
and then I find you
and then they can presenter
so that should work so if you share now
they should
okay let's see so I told you I'm a
complete novice you're a Zuma another
another teams are
so how do I share
does he not have a top right that was
um yeah
Fair tray icon okay yes it says open
share tray okay that's another
roundabout way of saying you want to
share okay okay
we've got
um
okay so we're having
oh yeah okay yeah I think if we close
that side then that's pretty good let's
listen yeah so we're good good from our
end is everyone online is okay
well let's see
so we've got um
two weeks till we begin
okay great
how's it going I'm woken you up too
early in California
uh not too too early
what is it it's nice yeah it's
yeah uh that's the problem of living on
the very west coast of the world is that
everyone else wakes up too early
but
I like the miracle we can we can do this
sort of thing right I was gonna say I
really like the ability to give talks
without leaving my house so
definitely worth it
so yeah you were wondering about
recording we couldn't still be going
okay I'm gonna do it again
I know it is in the process of
recordings that's fine okay great uh
so we'll wait till
did I quit it 10 minutes to the hour
um yeah I mean you know it's funny so
philosophy talks I remember the first
time I gave a talk to um
you kind of you know you're expected to
do about two to one ratio of talk to
questions and that some places even
worse than that and then you go there
and the Massachusetts wouldn't have
really good questions to put you
95 talk isn't it and five percent
questions but
um
okay well I'll try to
I'll try to leave time for questions I
should okay yeah I'm raising lots of
questions still okay
okay so I guess we're there so let's get
started so uh well
gosh what an influence John John had in
my life uh there I was a fledgling
philosopher trying to uh interested in
in mathematics
and and gone through his writings in the
in the Long Way a long time ago in the
1990s gave me the confidence to think
that you you could get access to the
Forefront of of mathematical and phys
scientific knowledge
through his writings I mean what gosh
what a what a joy that was to to engage
with his writings back at that time huge
influence on me and you know a bunch of
people will know that we started a Blog
together a while ago we had a lot of
conversations over over a great many
years
so it's great pleasure to have him speak
to us here today on on the play category
Theory so thank you John
well thanks very much thanks for
inviting me here uh the influence was
reciprocal uh it's really
exciting to think that what one is doing
in mathematics could actually be
interesting to a philosopher so that uh
one isn't just like fiddling around with
obscure equations
uh so I want to talk about applied
category Theory which is the latest turn
in this game
uh and
I'll talk more about the history of the
subject and what people are trying to do
then
uh any mathematics per se
I've given lots of talks about the
mathematics and so of all the people who
I'll be
referring to here so it's certainly easy
to click on any of the links in my
slides and get into the actual
mathematics but I'll try to not say
as much about that as I sometimes do
so
we often have this picture of different
uh
disciplines or subject areas
talking to their neighbors and
information flowing between pure math
which is at some very abstract and
uh to say the business World which is
maybe at the very concrete end in stages
with each discipline talking mainly to
its neighbors so care mathematicians
talk to applied mathematicians they give
suggestions to applied mathematicians
and they find out about problems from
applied mathematicians
and learn techniques from applied
mathematicians and similarly for each
link down the chain with each uh
discipline talking to its neighbors and
in this model which of course is very
oversimplified and and you can easily
find a lot of
faults in it
in this model we could think of category
Theory as the purest of pure some super
pure mathematics that only can talk to
mathematicians who then relay their
insights down the chain to the other
more practical subjects
um
I think that's what a lot of people
implicitly feel about category Theory or
at least used to uh and so when people
started talking about applied category
Theory people laughed because it sounds
like an oxymoron it just goes completely
against this picture here
however I think this picture is
inaccurate
um
for one thing a very important fact is
that starting maybe around 1980 or so it
became clear that computer science
really cuts across this traditional flow
of information computer science
interacts
almost directly with every single
piece of this chain
computer science has a big relation to
category Theory which I'll explain but
it also has a huge relation to other
aspects of
pure mathematics
and Applied Mathematics and so on down
to business so business
businesses will need to keep abreast of
developments in computer science and so
on basically
we now
communicate and think with the help of
these machines called computers that we
have devised to help us and and they
changed the whole game at every single
step of the way
now I have this crazy idea that maybe
category Theory actually really should
be thought of in a somewhat similar way
as interacting with all the different
links in the chain from the pure end to
the applied end rather than being tucked
away at the super pure end of the
spectrum now at first it seems
ridiculous and are laughable I mean for
starters category theory is sort of
nothing compared to computer science
everybody's walking around carrying cell
phones
um nobody's even heard of categories by
comparison so category Q is an ant
compared to the elephant of computer
science
however I'm thinking about what could be
uh not what yet is and secondly
when you think about how computers have
unified the whole chain
it's done so by means of the internet
which is an enormous Network
and category Theory isn't nothing if not
the mathematics of of networks or the
science of networks it's other things
too I shouldn't have said it quite that
way I mean it's it is the science of
networks but it does many other things
too uh
so
so really devise
good methods of getting computers to do
what we want
you need a way to think about them and I
think category theory is one of the
important ways to think about them
so you may think this is
ridiculous still because for example if
category theory was talking directly to
business
you'd expect that people would be going
into business during category Theory or
something like that setting up category
Theory businesses that sounds sort of
silly but in fact it's true so in fact
people are setting up category Theory
businesses and that's part of the kind
of thing I want to talk about I want to
talk about how category theory is now
being used at all
uh steps along this spectrum and for
that reason my talk will be less focused
on the math than on the history of how
category Theory became applied giving
you a flavor of how it's being applied
and pointing out some of the challenges
that show up
um uh before I can dive in I should say
that this history is going to be
extremely self-centered I'm not really
in a position to write a good or talk
about a good history of
category Theory so hopefully someone who
eventually tries to write a history of
Applied category Theory will listen to
this talk and fold it in as one data
point uh I'll talk about a lot of people
but I will also leave out a lot of
people and I really apologize to all the
people whose work on applied category
Theory I'm not mentioning
uh there's just no way for me to do a
fair treatment of this big subject
okay so I'll start arbitrarily in 1963
when Bill of beer introduced a concept
called frontorial semantics
so it's a very general concept where
you have a category
that describes uh syntax describes ways
of writing things down
and then
you describe the process of interpreting
those expressions or giving a meaning to
those expressions the factor
so from the functor will send
expressions
to their meanings but a crucial aspect
of this whole setup is that there's not
one god-given functor F that does this
you can choose various functors from the
category C to various other categories
he
uh because there are different ways to
assign meanings to expressions and that
flexibility is very important
and it became important in computer
science
so for example there's a
a nice there's a way to think about it
we're a sufficiently well behaved uh
programming language may give a category
where you think of the objects as types
or data types we've already heard about
that idea uh so types x y z Etc and then
amorphism between objects like amorphism
f from X to Y we think of it as a
program that accepts data of Type X as
input and outputs data of type y
and then the fact that you can compose
morphisms
tells you that you can hook up two
programs to get a bigger program where
the output of the first
program becomes the input of the second
and like that
that combination is a program in itself
so I could say this like the
relationship between the Lambda calculus
which is sort of an idealized
programming language simplified
programming language and Cartesian
closed categories uh understood by labik
is an example of this Paradigm of using
functorial semantics for uh
for computer science but here I'm only
so far talked about the category C I
haven't talked about the uh the functor
so what the functor could do well we
could for example take a function from
our category to the category of sets
not each data type X to a set and that
would be the set of possible values of
the of that data so like you could have
a data type like real numbers and then
definitely map it to the actual set of
real numbers
uh and then each program gets mapped
ideally to a function and the key factor
of a functor is that it preserves
composition so that composing programs
would compose the would give rise to
composing the functions they compute
and the identity
program which does nothing at all
you interpreted the Sumter f it gives
you the identity function which does
nothing at all on a set
so that's a that's a paradigm that
became important in theoretical computer
science I wouldn't say that most uh
computer scientists know or care about
frontorial semantics but in a certain
community of the more mathematical
theoretical computer scientists this
idea has become quite important
and there are certain languages like
Haskell for example and others that that
really take advantage of this uh
Viewpoint in particular Haskell uses a
category theoretic construct called
monads which has sent many uh
generations of young computer scientists
running for for help from a category
theorists to try to figure out what a
monad is I don't want to explain what a
monad is it's a category theoretic
construct which like many other
constructs uh become important when you
start thinking about programming in this
punctural synaptics way
but in the 1980s something very
different happened uh particle
physicists realized that any Quantum
field Theory specifies a category and
now the objects are roughly speaking
collections of particles and the
morphisms are roughly speaking ways for
particles to interact and turn into
other particles and in fact Feynman Drew
pictures called Feynman diagrams
for describing how particles interact
with each other this was a bold move
because although it seems very intuitive
here you have a proton and an
anti-proton coming in from the left and
then they Collide and all sorts of other
particles shoot out
uh in reality particles are not little
dots moving along little straight lines
quantum mechanics says that particles
are are wave like in character uh so
when Feynman introduced this pictorial
language you've got a lot of opposition
from older uh Quantum physicists like
heisenbergen and Bohr uh and yet it
turned out Feynman was correct in doing
this what finding diagrams actually are
later became clear much later is there
pictures of morphisms in specific
categories and each individual Quantum
field Theory gives a category and then
that determines what allowed Feynman
diagrams you can write so if you have a
theory that
doesn't have quarks in it you're not
allowed to write this q line for for
quark
um
and then what do you do with these
pictures Well you your goal in in
particle physics is to compute a bunch
of numbers like what's the probability
that if I smack two particles into each
other that some other particle shoots
out so for calculating numbers we need
uh to interpret our finding diagram that
is in the functorial semantics attitude
we need to functor from our category to
some other category which assigns
meaning to the finding diagrams in this
category we could take to be the
category of Hilbert spaces a widely
loved mathematical structure in quantum
mechanics and so then it will this
function will turn any Feynman diagram
into amorphism in the category of
Hilbert's faces and that's called a
linear operator between Hilbert spaces
and so you can look at what physicists
are doing with Feynman diagrams uh as
basically using them as a syntax which
they then apply the semantics to to then
grind out numbers
now Feynman probably would have laughed
at this whole business because he knew
what he was doing he didn't need any
category theorists to tell him what what
he was doing but by the 1980s particle
physics had become elaborate enough and
deeply connected with enough pure
mathematics that this attitude of
thinking of upon field theory in terms
of functorial semantics became a really
profitable attitude you could do things
with category theory that particle
physicists were struggling to do without
category Theory and so it helped
and this led to a whole line of work uh
trying to relate category Theory to
quantum mechanics
and in 2004 Samson abramski and Bob
kirka wrote a very influential paper
showing that a certain Quantum process
that goes by the name quantum
teleportation
and also other
processes could be understood using
category Theory and using diagrams that
resemble find the diagrams but here the
edges in these diagrams which now I
guess we're reading from top to bottom
rather than across the edges are not
describing Elementary particles but just
states of an arbitrary
Quantum system so it could be an
electron or it could be some larger
system and I don't want to try to
explain this in detail but there are but
these are pictures of morphisms in some
category
and they're equal to each other
and these morphisms describe some
process where one participant always is
called Alice in cryptography uh
communicates a message to another
participant it's called Bob
and in quantum teleportation
you have the superficial appearance that
you're communicating uh faster than
light
but in fact what's really going on is
that you've laid the ground for the
communication by some classical process
that has already transferred some
information and then the rest of the
information uh is transferred on the
basis of that
in any event quantum teleportation was a
sort of magical wonderful thing that you
can do in quantum mechanics and this
gave a kind of category Theory theoretic
account for how it how it's working
and that was quite exciting to people
because it took the quantum applications
of category Theory out of the realm of
elementary particle physics and into a
new realm that was developing which is
quantum information Theory or Quantum
computation
which has the potential for being a
quite practical thing and indeed already
a Quantum cryptography is a is is it is
used
so on the basis of this and other work
and also on the basis I should say over
a huge amount of Charisma Bob Kirker and
Samson abramsky
built a huge group of people at Oxford
sometimes called the quantum group
working on category Theory the
foundations of quantum physics and
Quantum computation one interesting
thing about this enormous group here is
that it's in the computer science
department so not a mathematics
Department not even a physics department
but a computer science department here's
Samson abrovsky here and here's Bob
kirka looking sort of disreputable over
on the edge that's completely
intentional he's like that and here are
many many people including I see Jules
Hedges who has mentioned uh
in the previous talk that you were
example categorical cybernetics
um so Circa and co-authors developed
this diagrammatic method for explaining
quantum physics
and they eventually decided it would be
very good to write a textbook on this
and so here's one of the two textbooks
that Bob kruka helped write on pictorial
methods of understanding quantum physics
and the one interesting thing about this
book so first of all I recommend this
book if you're interested in learning
category Theory from a unorthodox and
sort of easier
approach than the conventional one
because it's very pictorial uh but I
mentioned it because part of what what
you wound up doing is hiding the
category theory in the sense that you
don't run around saying category and
functor and all sorts of other jargon
like that a lot instead you draw
pictures of processes and you explain
these pictures in a Hands-On way and you
explain how you can stick one picture
onto the other which is composing
morphisms but you don't say the word
composing morphisms necessarily because
you don't need to
uh and this is one of a generation I
should say a new generation of category
Theory textbooks that are part of the
applied category Theory movement so if a
category theory is going to reach
directly to many different communities
at different stages of the knowledge
chain that I drew at the top of the talk
uh it means that you can't force people
to first become mathematicians before
they then start doing things with
category Theory the traditional approach
to category Theory treats category
theories like some finishing school that
you engage in after you've already
learned abstract algebra and this and
that and algebraic topology and so on
that's just too onerous a path to
category theory if you're trying to get
a computer scientists much less business
people to get some inkling of category
Theory and it's not really necessary to
take that elaborate route because
category 30 is something so fundamental
that it can be explained more directly I
especially recommend Eugenia Chang's
book The Joy of abstraction which is a
really wonderful introduction to
category theory for people who have not
had much prior exposure to mathematics
at all and it goes all the way up to the
Oneida embedding theorem
thank you
so in 2021 Perka actually left Oxford
University and he became the chief
scientist of a company called Continuum
which uses category theory for Quantum
Computing and also natural language
processing
this is a picture of him on the
Continuum web page
as you can see he's trying to quite hard
not to fall into the stereotypical
academic image here he's a great guy by
the way you shouldn't mind me teasing
him like this uh
I think though that it is important it's
having people with personalities who are
willing to break out of the
stereotypical mold of
a
math professor is important in this
whole category Theory
application movement
uh I should say that there's a lot of
interaction between
Quantum Computing ideas and natural
language processing ideas which I won't
really have time to get into
uh to some extent they were visible in
the last talk but if you want a real
emphasis on the natural language
processing aspect The Works of uh Tai
Denae Bradley are very good she's
another
newer explainer of category Theory it's
a non-category theorists and she is also
working uh in a company that
uses Quantum methods and categorical
methods for natural language processing
but Ontario semantics is extremely
General so we it's not just applicable
to the topics that I've already
mentioned so in lots of areas of Science
and Engineering people use a syntax
where
you you draw diagrams
and then a semantics where you convert
those diagrams into math which is very
often the systems of
differential equations you're describing
how things change in time you're
describing dynamical systems uh
so you use differential equations
but the interesting part is that hooking
up
diagrams to each other is actually
composing morphisms in a category
and the fact that you're
you're working with frontorial semantics
says that when you compose
those morphisms in the syntax category
your functor
will map it the resulting composite to
the composite of the two systems of
differential equations that each picture
separately is mapped to so in other
words there's another category lurking
around here where the morphisms are
actually systems of differential
equations
systems of differential equations with
some specified inputs and outputs to
surface
as the source and target of your
morphism here are some different
pictures you've seen a bunch of these
types of pictures I hope so electrical
circuit diagrams are are one of the
earliest and very widely used
um
this thing here is a called a petri net
and it's a petri nut of a particular
model for the AIDS
virus and its interaction with blood
cells infection of of white blood cells
this here is a very small uh diagram in
the subject of control theory where you
have some process in an industrial plant
that you're trying to keep under control
and so you take feedback you read off
information from that process and you
use it to feedback
affect the the process itself to keep it
on track I mean the very simplest
example here would be like a thermostat
but in in industrial chemistry they
become much more elaborate
and so there's a whole diagrammatic
language of control theory that you can
read about in textbooks on that subject
and this is a
little diagram of some molecules in
molecular biology molecular biology or
biochemistry they have so many different
diagram languages that in fact they've
set up a committee on to standardize the
diagram languages so that people reading
different biochemistry papers can look
at the diagrams and not have to be
explained each time what the diagrams
mean but it's sufficiently Baroque that
they uh that the committee wound up
choosing three different diagram
languages because they they need
multiple languages to describe different
things they're interested in
so these are very widespread and the
people in these different subjects don't
think of what they're doing here as
category Theory they don't think of it
as mathematics they think of it as this
is the stuff we draw
to understand the differential equations
that you can convert these pictures into
the equations of the math but these
pictures are our own private little
trick for understanding what's going on
but I claim that these pictures are
actually also mathematics and they're
these diagrams are morphisms in various
categories which are using punctural
synaptics to convert to differential
equations
like
excited that had to be true and I wanted
to work out the details
around 2012 so I asked
Brendan Fawn who eventually became my
grad student to
tackle what I thought would be a very
good first example namely electrical
circuits
because everybody knows about electrical
circuits and the mathematics of them is
in substance very well understood
linear electrical circuits for example
made out of just resistors or maybe
capacitors and inductors as well
um
I asked them to create and study a
category having open electrical circuits
as morphism so these are electrical
circuits which have certain things
hanging out which serves as inputs and
outputs I think in the last part they
are called cilia so these are just these
dots here
um so it took forever to do it so it
seemed but it turned out that what he
was doing was not just answering the
question that I asked but in fact
uh answering a much more general
question he invented a general theory
which he called decorated Coast bands
for handling this problem but also all
the other problems that I described that
is essentially all the other kinds of
diagram languages
all right showed can be understood using
the theory of decorated co-spans
although the details have to be
individually worked out in each case
this decorated co-span formalism is a is
a recipe for getting categories of this
General sort and so naturally it did
take him a while to do a good job of it
and he finished his thesis on it in
2016. I won't attempt to explain
decorated post bands any more than I
just have I've given lots of talks on
decorating post bands and you can see on
YouTube me giving talks about them if
you're interested
um I just want to mention one little
thing is that well first of all here's
Brennan Fong and here's another student
of mine Blake Pollard who together with
Brendan applied this theory of decorated
close bands to the second example that
we tackled which was Markov processes
honestly so so Blake did a lot of work
on Markov processes
uh and another thing I want to mention
is that uh Brendan went to
get his PhD at Oxford so he was in the
enormous group that I mentioned
and I believe Kirko is his de facto it
was his day jury advisor but in fact I
was the the de facto advisor telling you
important to Brendan about this this
problem uh and so nonetheless it's
really important that this large body of
people that uh at uh
at Oxford is is spreading across the
world doing many things and Brendan is
one of them
so after doing this doing his PhD uh
Brendan went to MIT in 2016 to work as a
postdoc with David Spivak so spivack is
another very important figure in applied
category Theory so among other things he
had helped to create a language for
databases called functorial query
language
which has now become the basis of a
company called Connexus AI with Ryan
wisniewsky as a as a head of that
company but David Spivak also involved
this
approach the databases really relies
heavily on functorial semantics so the
idea is the database schema is
is an object in some category and then
by a functor you can map it to a sort of
populated or inhabited database schema
where where the the
your table of is actually filled with
entries you can imagine like taking a
spreadsheet and actually typing in the
entries that's one possible uh
interpretation of of the abstract
database that has not yet been
interpreted with with specific people's
names and numbers
uh
and in 2014 David wrote a textbook on
this idea and others called category
theory for the Sciences so I also highly
recommend this as yet another uh of this
new generation of category Theory
textbooks it's trying to reach out
beyond the traditional confines of the
category Theory community
of Highly pure mathematicians toward
other audiences
and in 2010 2018 uh Brendan Fong and
David Spivak wrote another textbook
explicitly on applied category Theory
which is uh fondly called seven sketches
but its actual title is here earns lager
uh emphasizing the principle of
compositionality in many guises and they
taught a course on it which you can see
on YouTube if you click on this link in
my slides and the textbook is also
available for free on the archive as
well as
for purchase
and I'm mentioning this stuff about
things being available online for free
partially because when you're trying to
reach out
of the
pure math realm into the rest of the
world and teach the rest of the world
category Theory you quickly realize that
making things easily available for free
is going to speed up the process a lot
and so I think there's a general
commitment so far on the part of a lot
of Applied category theorists to make
things open source and uh easy to get at
now in 2018 my graduate student Kenny
corser there and I came up with
structured Coast Fans which is a simpler
alternative to decorated Coast bands
turns out to be not quite as flexible as
decorated Coast Fans but in many cases
either formalism works and in those
cases I'd say structured co-spans are
simpler in 2020 Christina vasilicopolu
who's standing to the left there uh
helped us understand how decorated and
structured Coast bands are related for a
while I thought structured Coast Fans
would replace decorated Coast Fans but
it turns out we we now see that they
can't cover quite as much territory and
that we really need decorated co-spans
in some case cases so the full story is
somewhat elaborate right now uh I've
given talks about that but it's it's
actually very pretty
so by now structured and decorated Coast
Fans have been used to study open
systems of many kinds so by open systems
I mean systems that have loose ends that
are meeting systems that are morphisms
in a category that you can stick
together or compose to get bigger
systems and
there were open graphs are just to
Simply a graph with Loose Ends it's very
combinatorial structure that's a very
simple example open Petri nuts is a more
useful example here's a picture of a an
open tetry net where you have
things describing are what they're
called
called places that could represent like
populations of different kinds of
chemicals or organisms and then you have
these blue boxes called transitions
which describe how things can come out
of various places and turn into things
of other kinds
um if you attach numbers to these
transitions uh describing the rate at
which the transition tends to occur you
get something called a open Petri net
with rates or maybe an open chemical
reaction network with rates
uh
and my student Blake Pollard worked on
those open electrical circuits I've
mentioned open Markov processes I
mentioned open dynamical systems those
at the systems of differential equations
interpreted as morphisms in some
category
so there are papers on all of these and
if you click on these Brown things
you'll get to those papers
so at a certain point I thought that
maybe someday all of this would lead to
some unified language of the Sciences
and my ambition
which seems very limited in retrospect
was that by
interacting with Scientists maybe
eventually
this unified language would help
scientists in one discipline talk to
scientists in another discipline and
share tricks of various sorts
but then something quite different
happened which is much more exciting in
my mind namely in 2019
James Fairbanks is an engineer and Evan
Patterson who was a statistics
PhD began developing a computer system
called algebraic Julia
for it's a system for high performance
scientific computing
built on the language called Julia
which is designed for crunching numbers
really fast
but
algebraic Julia lets you program it
using constructs from category Theory so
in algebraic Julia you can talk about
categories functors and all these other
things that category theorists like to
talk about and write your programs using
those contents so it's a very very high
level system but coupled to the raw
computational power of algebraic Julia
so now we're attractive revolutionize
scientific Computing in this way
and in 2020
Evan implemented structured co-spans in
algebraic Julia
and then using this system uh for the
example of open Tech units he and Mika
halter
reconstructed some of a covid-19 model
which was currently being used by the UK
government
so the UK government had a very
elaborate model of covid-19 with many
populations of different people with
different conditions possibly living in
different locations Etc uh and then I
can start the populations of these
orange boxes and able to turn into other
kinds of people via these transitions in
blue
the
whole model is much larger than this
this is just a tiny fraction of it and
what
they wanted to demonstrate was that you
could build the whole model by building
smaller models and pieces and then
subsequently sticking together those
pieces
which is in fact something that had not
been done before models were sort of had
to be constructed in whole cloth by
essentially by one person keeping track
of the whole thing
but this is a new approach compositional
epidemiology and so it attracted the
attention of some epidemiologists
especially since covid-19 was a very
live issue at the time
then in a different direction in 2021
Brendan Fong and David Spivak who had
been remembered over at MIT decided to
quit traditional Academia and start
their own Institute called The topus
Institute in downtown Berkeley
it's an Institute for Applied
Mathematics
but with a heavy slant on applied
category Theory
and they hired a number of people
including Evan Patterson and also Sophie
Lipkin who's here who will appear later
in the story
and it's a real real incubator for our
ideas on applied category Theory now
and so this is another one of the
sociological moves that I had to be made
I think to bring applied category Theory
forward I recommended Brendan not try to
start an Institute right after his first
postdoc but luckily he was much braver
than I would ever be and he went ahead
and did it and it's quite successful now
so in 2022
Sophie Lipkin Mika halter Evan Patterson
James Fairbanks and another person I
haven't mentioned Andrew boss used
algebraic Julia
to systematically
build models of epidemia
epidemiology using open Petri Nets with
raids so here are some open Petri Nets
the rates that is the number data is not
being shown here and here they're being
stuck together to form a larger
open Petri net the way that they're
being stuck together you'll notice is
not end to end this is not the normal
end-to-end composition that you see in a
category this is something a little bit
more General
for sticking them together using a trick
called an operand so operatic
composition is one of the things that
they Incorporated in their algebraic
Jewelers software which is
this was done this previous work was
done in a slightly hot basis but but
this really used operats in the
systematic way
and then in 2022 also
another team of people including myself
used to algebraic Julia to create
software for building models of
epidemiology using another style of
diagrams called open Stock flow diagrams
well stock flow diagrams but we're
making them open so here are some of
those kind of diagrams being stuck
together in an operatic style that is
not end to end but sort of gluing them
all together to form a bigger model
so part of the point here is that when
we started talking to actual
epidemiologists
we applied category theorists learned
more about how they actually want to do
their models and they didn't really want
to do their models using pepinance
primarily they wanted to use a different
technique that they considered congenial
called stock flow diagrams
um so in fact there's a community of
epidemiologists who use stock flow
diagrams to model the spread of disease
and it includes my co-authors Nathaniel
Osgood and his grad student xiaoyen Lee
and one crucial fact is that they did
covid modeling for the government of
Canada so they were requested by the
government of Canada to set up covid
models for the a number of different
provinces
and in the process they gained a lot of
experience uh with stock flow models
they already had a lot of experience and
they wouldn't have been asked to do it
but they gained a lot more experience
and they learned some of the problems of
the existing technology
this is a beautiful thing about stock
flow diagrams which is that with a
little bit of just a little bit of
training you can read them and you can
understand what they're talking about so
a fellow named Hoffman has pushed the
idea of community-based modeling where
you go to a community that has some
problem like a disease or some other
type of problem and you help model it
and you model it by drawing stock flow
diagrams which here are hanging on the
wall in a in a room in rural India
and that people can
look at those diagrams and comment on
them and help you improve the model
because these people the the local
people they will have the knowledge of
what's actually going on that the you
the modeler who just flew in from from
Oxford or wherever may not have and here
we see a woman here looking at the
picture on the wall and this is actually
from a story where this woman noticed
that some ingredient was being left out
of the model uh that these Village
Elders hadn't known about or had thought
about and so she helped fix the model
so that's the example of what you can do
and you'll notice that none of the
people in this story here had to know
category Theory but they were in fact uh
drawing more systems in the category on
the notes to themselves
now most stock flow modeling in the
commercial level or the hype or the
government level is done using a piece
of software called any logic which is
very powerful but it has several big
problems
it doesn't let you compose models it
lets you make a model but it doesn't let
you take a bunch of models and stick
them together
it doesn't separate syntax from
semantics it only has one semantics
namely the differential equation
semantics which is the most important
semantics but there are others that you
would like
it has no support for what's called
stratifying models that term was very
confusing to me it's sort of charging in
on this community what it means is
taking a model and splitting One stock
one type of group of people into several
stocks so for example you might have a
simple model and then you may say oh we
should subdivide people according to age
groups because older people who get the
disease more more than younger people or
something like that and you would like
your software to make it easy to to do
that
um it had no support for collaboratively
building models it's basically one
person as the software and they make the
model they could talk to other people
but they're the one who's building the
model
and it's not free it's commercial piece
of software and it's not open source so
people can't get in there and modify it
and improve it
so our new work and to fix all these
problems and I could say we're well on
the way to fixing all these problems
so the reason it's so important to
produce models is that the models that
get actually used in the real world are
immensely complex so here's a picture of
Osgood and Lee's covid model this is a
page in any logic the software this is
the whole model as you can see it's an
enormous web of of stocks and flows and
such and you you really would prefer
actually not to have to deal with this
whole entity at at once you prefer to
have it be thought of as being made up
out of smaller pieces because mentally
it is made up out of smaller pieces uh
but but that's not captured by the the
software unfortunately any logic just
doesn't do that for you
so we've not created software that does
that it supports compositional modeling
with the stock flow diagrams so it's
called stock flow and if you click on
this link you'll go to GitHub which is
where computer programmers keep their
open source software so you can get
download the software
and so it lets you create and compose
open Stock flow diagrams and lets you
stratify them that is subdivide stocks
into smaller stocks for those of you who
like category Theory I'll mention that
that's done using a technique called
pullbacks in category Theory it lets you
choose among several different semantics
functors so one of which is the
differential equation semantics
uh and of course it lets you solve the
differential equations once you get them
and then Nate Osgood and another student
of his Eric redika went further and made
a graphical user interface for stock
flow so stock flow is written in this
programming language called algebraic
Julia to interact with it you needed to
know algebraic Julia
but this graphical inner graphical user
interface called Model collab it runs on
a browser and you manipulate the the
model by actually dragging and dropping
little boxes and drawing little edges
between boxes
still
uh and because it runs on multiple
browsers teams of different people
located in different locations can a lot
can collaborate to build stock flow
diagrams so I could build my piece you
could build your piece we could both
save them they'd be saved on the on the
cloud and I see there's this little
thing called Cloud here uh that that's
not what it is actually for them sorry
that's a mistake uh but but you can you
can say it's gonna laugh at that
um actually clouds are these little
funny things here
uh but you can say you can save your
models on the uh on the internet and so
that other people in different locations
can access them and then glue them
together to form larger models
so in the goal to really apply
mathematics there are many levels
because the next step is to actually
train epidemiologists to use model
collab so we have some things going for
us so first of all eight Osgood runs
regular training sessions which goes by
the Quasi militaristic terminology
favored in computer science of boot
camps because they're supposed to be
intense so it runs boot camps on
epidemiological modeling so he is
beginning to teach people model cloud
second no understanding of category
Theory or the programming language Julia
is required to use model collab so it's
really crucial when you're applying
category three that you can ultimately
Black Box the category theory in it so
that people do not explicitly need to
know it to use what you're creating
although they may be using it in some
kind of implicit way
uh and third it's free while any logic
you have to pay for which should
ultimately be an advantage
but I should still say it will take a
lot of work because when you have a
generation of modelers trying to use any
logic this new paradigm is not so easy
to shape
so as I just already said applying
mathematics takes many steps and as I've
moved from being more of a pure
mathematician towards a bit more at
least some some days of the week of an
applied mathematician I realize how easy
peer mathematicians have it you just
write a paper you explain your idea you
throw it out there and you hope that
somebody reads it but when you're trying
to actually carry out the full
application of an idea you have to
interact with many people with many
skills persuade many different
communities that what you're doing is
actually worth doing and it's much more
elaborate but I should also say very
satisfying endeavor
laughs so I'll conclude by saying that
applied category theory is interesting
in in many ways some of which I hope
will be interesting to philosophers
uh so
some of these ways are separate from
sort of the core mathematical ideas so
one thing as I hope I've Illustrated
here
by my somewhat self-centered history is
that it requires new forms of
communication and collaboration because
you're talking to new types of people
and luckily uh
these are starting to come into
existence so there's an annual
applied category Theory conference
that's first started in 2018
uh run that time by Brendan Fong and
some of his other young friends
another is a journal so there's a
journal
called compositionality which is again
started by Brendan falling in some of
his
collaborators and friends this is an
open access free to publish free to read
Journal of Applied category Theory which
I recommend to your attention
and another is called the category
Theory Community server which is sort of
like a a chat site or a discussion site
for Applied category Theory actually for
all category three but it has a lot of
Applied category theorists there uh this
was initiated by my grad student
Christian Williams
and so these are different ways for
category theorists to start talking to
other kinds of people people who want to
might want to apply category Theory or
learn category three and I hope that
these catalyze the the
process done
trying to outline here
another thing is that category Theory
raises ethical issues in ways that
category theorists aren't used to
pure mathematicians tend to feel
themselves somewhat insulated from a lot
of ethical issues because
what although their math make it used
for all sorts of purposes
they don't consider themselves
particularly responsible for how their
mathematics gets used because it's so
abstracted they sort of can blame
someone else for understanding it and
doing something with it
um
but when you start doing explicitly
applied to category theory that sort of
veil of uh protection is is ripped open
and you see that what you're doing may
have a fairly immediate effect
so for example the biggest funder of
research on applied category theory is
currently the US military right now
and also a lot of Applied category
theory is being used for artificial
intelligence or machine learning or
large language models or so on
so I'm not saying that those are
necessarily bad things I'm saying that
those are things that definitely raise
serious ethical issues
and so I'm worried about the danger that
applied category Theory will wind up
merely intensifying
deal already existing
patterns in society that is it will only
make the richest and most powerful
people even richer and more powerful
I would prefer it if applied category
Theory could do something really
different really new this is one reason
why I've tried to focus on epidemiology
which is a little bit different than
than some of the other
uh applications of course even at the
demiology ultimately feeds into the
healthcare system so there are questions
about that as well I would really like
to use applied category theory for
environmental issues uh but I haven't
quite gotten there yet
anyway sorry I just wanted to emphasize
that uh
you know ethics is the provenance of
philosophers and this is a really
interesting intersection of mathematics
and ethics which I hope that people
think about
and another thing applied category three
does is Revitalize what is a very old
question which mathematical structures
are best for describing and designing
systems I emphasize designing because
with the
rise of computers whatever you can think
about clearly enough you can make so
it's not merely describing the external
world it's you're also making worlds
based on your descriptions and so this
immense Freedom that you have in
computer science that the question is
what's what should guide you and it
opens progress it opens possibilities
for some really radical progress because
these are some really brand new ideas
that we're talking about here that make
let us organize systems in new ways
so I think there's a lot to think about
here and I hope
I hope some people here uh
give it a try
okay I think I'll
declare it done
brilliant
you can see why I got drawn in by him 30
years ago it's uh
his ways of conveying ideas so clearly
okay do
let's have some some questions then
um
let me bring up the
people perhaps if people online have
some questions that
they can raise a hand and I
hopefully should be able to see
or anyone here
uh okay uh Mark's but I I do have a
question and I'm I
I'm finding stuff that I've thanks for
that by the way
um this is really exciting stuff for me
but I'm wondering if I'm biased in
reading too much into this that uh uh
that just works in my self-interest
um I do philosophy of time and um I'm
one of the uh the few people who defend
the notion that time flows and uh
um I see in your work uh but I'm uh
maybe it's through these biased eyes
that uh this uh this project is bringing
back the idea of uh of thinking of uh
differential equations for instance as
things that flow uh that functions or
something that flow and I noticed the
importance of diagrams as uh and these
diagrams of uh uh uh are reminiscent of
what organizations would call flow
charts and uh um I'm I I'm wondering
whether I'm reading too much into this
as something that might be an answer to
the the static view of uh of uh in in in
maths that came out of uh set theory and
uh uh um thinking of uh um functions as
uh as something that uh is static and
not doesn't float so I'm I'm wondering
whether or not I'm reading too much into
it so maybe maybe that's the question
sure
um yeah the question of static versus
Dynamic is as you know very well or
extremely tricky question because I
could take any dynamical system and
when it's when it's done or when we
imagine it as being
laid out in time then we can think of it
as a static thing with time is just
another space like Dimension and and I
think there's three
it's very hard to like definitively
break out of that uh so but nonetheless
category theory is a generalization of
set theory in a sense in which instead
of just having elements in a set you
have objects and also morphisms and the
morphisms have are meant to convey some
kind of dynamic
that aspect of the system that is a
amorphism goes from an object to an
object and that's a very primitive sense
of Dynamics there of the the start and
the end and and and it brings a kind of
dynamical quality to to the foundations
of mathematics which is is a real thing
it's not it's not just an illusion uh I
mean even though you could if you ask a
traditional mathematician what is a
category and there's a oh it's a set of
objects and a set of morphisms and some
functions doing this and that right so
you could say oh or just back in the
same old Paradigm and that's what I
meant by it's hard to definitively break
out of that Paradigm I I think it's more
in some ways more of a question of
attitude rather than than anything else
uh
and anyway I think the interesting thing
about the differential equations here
may be the interesting new thing maybe
the study of open differential equations
which are differential equations where
some quantities are explicitly labeled
as
affected by the outside world affected
by the part of the world which is not
modeled by the differential equation so
uh traditional differential equations
well no physics often like the study
what are called autonomous systems of
differential equations where
you know everything there is to know
once you know the differential equations
uh where as open differential equations
which I should say are also studied by
persistent especially Engineers have
certain quantities which are not
determined by the differential equation
they're regarded as being
affected by the outside world and and
that that on the one hand allows you to
treat systems differential equations as
morphisms that could stick together by
sticking some of these
quantities on the edge to some other
quantities on the edge but it also means
that you're you're not just dealing with
a deterministic system in the classic
sense anymore because you have
quantities that are affected by the
unknown so so they it definitely changes
your attitude towards differential
equations
thanks uh a question from Toby
it's not so much a question sorry
although I would love to I mean there's
also there's questions I could ask but I
I need to head off because I actually
have to go give this talk again just now
thank you very much for inviting me and
uh I hope the discussion is profitable
okay thanks baby
uh I had a um I was telling the
interests a lot of people around here is
is the difference between when you get
variables that are just sort of
associated with each other there's some
kind of statistical Association versus
when you think there's some kind of
causal connection between them
uh and you might think you might think
you're a much better grip on the world
if it isn't just Association data but
there's a you've got a you know the a
causes B
other ways of getting at this through
your
um or is it is it that you you I guess
the modelers are kind of coming already
with their sense of what causes wild and
is there any way of representing the
difference
yeah so this particular
line of work that I was outlining as you
say
I was mainly most of my talk was about
model building where you you have your
opinion about what causes what and how
it
affect what how X affects Y and you
build the model into that so there's a
flip side of the whole um modeling
process which I didn't talk about at all
which is incredibly important in
epidemiology which is
you know inference so you you measure
data and you try to establish
causality and also various numerical
quantities which you would then put into
your model
um so
so there's a lot to applied category
theory has to offer to that and I'm
afraid I'm not quite as uh knowledgeable
about that I will say that
um Brendan Fong for his master's thesis
uh worked on a categorical approach to
uh Bayesian networks and so and and and
that is subsequently grown into things
like what uh Toby was discussing
uh and so that should that's that's also
part of a big story and another part of
it is that
there's a technique called
uh particles filtering
where you which is widely used by
epidemiologists where once you have one
of your models of the sort that I've
been discussing
you run it and you run it a bunch of
times and you see what kind of outcomes
it predicts but then you use that to uh
to compare to reality and you use that
to estimate the parameters that you'd be
in your model
so so I guess what you could say is that
like what I've been describing was just
sort of one half of a feedback loop of
interaction between modeling and then
comparing model with reality and and
yeah so the whole thing should be should
be carefully understood and I'm afraid I
have sort of focused on one half of it
sure yeah I've seen various diagrammatic
techniques from category theorists and
really get it kind of causal modeling I
mean that exists out there doesn't it
yeah it does and that's important
okay um
well at this I think there's no further
questions when we reached six o'clock
anyway so let's just oh sorry was there
one there was a one sorry there's
dominance gone here you go yes sorry I'm
casting around I have lots of things to
say sort of trying to formulate them
into the questions typical hi John uh
um so one thing that in um I know in
computer science is quite a big deal of
sort of algorithms and data structures
um and kind of getting the right data
structure for the right task to get good
performance
um and
I think you know there's a lot of things
that category theory has to say about
this um
uh kind of describing data structures in
in a more abstract way sort of
polynomial functions and things like
this
um so
what I haven't quite sort of understood
is is how much of that kind of work is
going on in in the applied category sort
of movement recently sort of linking
with
with back back with computer science the
sort of like programming aspects around
what I would call kind of classical
compute science of algorithms and data
structures
um do you know if there's much of much
of that going on within the sort of act
World
um or is that
um largely more back with the computer
scientists
um so the algebraic Julia Community is
really trying to
blend
uh
computer programming with category
theory in a really rich way so that you
can write software and you can say you
know Define functor define pre-shift
category blood so that that and that's
just one of several different
initiatives to try to
bring category Theory into programming
so not just have it help programming it
but I would actually be part of the
programming so that that's one thing
there are lots of other things and I
probably don't know the other things so
I will just mention again this company
uh connexus.ai uses uh categorical
approach to databases so it turns out
that the updating databases is very
nicely described using
uh
categorical ideas like on extensions and
um Mike Johnson in Australia has been
serving as a consultant for uh for
database companies using category Theory
ideas uh for many years but now this
company based on David spivex work is is
also doing that
uh and there are and there are a lot of
other things I should say that there's
just
a lot more on the computer science side
that I'm not very familiar with
okay all right okay thank you very much
okay so well here we've reached home so
let's what we have to do is thank John
very much for his for his very
interesting talk
[Applause]
so I've recorded the session and we can
uh
you said you're thinking putting it
online we could yeah I'd like to if
that's acceptable trip yeah yeah let's
do that good all right okay well thanks
thanks ever so much John okay thanks
very much
bye bye everyone online bye I'll see you
see you look like
[Music]
all right